# Dipendra Yadav

+49-3834-420-5507 | dipendra.yadav@uni-greifswald.de

☐ dipen-yadav | ☐ dipen-yadav | ☐ google scholar

Rostock, Germany

# **Objective**

Machine Learning Researcher with a robust background in Natural Language Processing (NLP) and software engineering, currently dedicated to advancing the field of interpretability and explainability in machine learning models with a primary focus on the healthcare sector.

## Education

#### • University of Greifswald

January 2023 - Present

 $PhD\ Candidate$ 

Greifswald, Germany

• The doctoral research focuses on explainability methods for machine learning models (with a focus on large language models) in the healthcare domain.

#### • University of Rostock

 $October\ 2017\ \hbox{-}\ July\ 2020$ 

MSc in Electrical Engineering

Rostock, Germany

- German Grade: 1.5 (very good, where 1.0 is best and 5.0 is worst)
- · Concentration: Natural language processing, Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Software Engineering

#### • Visvesvaraya Technological University

2011 - 2015

Bachelor in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Bengaluru, India

• Grade: 76.53% (First Class with Distinction, 2nd rank in the class of 63 students)

# Professional Experience

#### • University of Rostock

January 2022 - September 2022

 $Research\ Assistant$ 

Rostock, Germany

- Researched in deep learning-based generative models like variational Autoencoders and GANs for neural density estimation.
- Contributed to the NEISS project, presenting a poster at the Abschluss-Seminar.

#### • PlanetAI GmbH

May 2020 - January 2022

 $Software\ Engineer$ 

Rostock, Germany

- $\circ$  Developed frontend and backend for Intelligent Document Analysis (IDA) software.
- Built CI/CD pipelines on DroneCI (reference letter).

#### • Market Logic Software

November 2019 - April 2020

Student Assistant Data Scientist

Research Intern and Master Thesis in NLP

Berlin, Germany

- Assisted in the research and development of NLP tools for analyzing Natural Language Data to support business insights.
- Extracted relevant information to optimize decision-making processes (Letter of Reference).

#### • PlanetAI GmbH

April 2019 - March 2020

Rostock, Germany

- Master Thesis: Researched state-of-the-art methods for transfer learning for Deep NLP systems on rarely annotated languages (Hindi and Nepali).
- $\circ$   $\mathbf{Internship:}$  Investigated and enhanced BLSTM-CNN-CRF model performance for NER through multitask learning.

## **Publications**

- [1] Yadav, Dipendra, et al. (2024). Cross-Lingual Named Entity Recognition for Low-Resource Languages: A Hindi-Nepali Case Study Using Multilingual BERT Models MRL@EMNLP2024: Proceedings of the 4th Workshop on Multi-lingual Representation Learning at EMNLP 2024. Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL).
- [2] Yadav, Dipendra, et. al (2024). A Comparative Analysis on Machine Learning Techniques for Research Metadata: the ARDUOUS Case Study. INFORMATIK 2024 Gesellschaft für Informatik e.V.
- [3] Yadav, Dipendra. (2023). Evaluating Dangerous Capabilities of Large Language Models: An Examination of Situational Awareness. DC@KI2023: Proceedings of Doctoral Consortium at KI 2023.
- [4] Yadav, Dipendra, et al. (2020). Exploring Transfer Learning for Deep NLP Systems on Rarely Annotated Languages. arXiv preprint 2410.12879.

# Teaching Assistant

Mathematics of Artificial Intelligence
 Winter Semester 2024/25, University of Greifswald

# Relevant Activities

- Selected by the German Centre for Research and Innovation for a two-week start-up tandem program hosted at IISc Bengaluru, India.
- Organized the 8th International Workshop on Annotation of useR Data for UbiquitOUs Systems at Informatik Festival 2024, Germany.
- Participated in the EuADS Summer School Generative AI 2024, Luxembourg.
- Selected for the fully-funded Swiss AI Safety Summer Camp 2023.
- Attended the AI Safety fundamentals alignment course by AI Safety Sweden.

## Honours and Awards

- Special Award for Digital Innovation and Process Optimization (2018).
- 3rd Place in the Graduate and Researcher category at the Idea Competition (2018).

#### Skills

- Programming Languages: Python, Java, Bash, Git.
- Frameworks: TensorFlow, Keras, Scikit-learn, Docker.
- Languages: German (Intermediate), English (Fluent), Hindi, Nepali, Mithali.

## References

- Prof. Dr.-Ing Kristina Yordanova University of Greifswald, Germany kristina.yordanova@uni-greifswald.de
- Dr. rer. nat. Tobias Strauß University of Rostock, Germany tobias.strauss@uni-rostock.de
- Dr. Emma Tonkin University of Bristol, United Kingdom E.L.Tonkin@bristol.ac.uk